Inventory of the Russian independent trade union publications collection, 1987-1999
Hoover Institution Archives
Russian independent trade union publications collection, 1987-1999
2009C16
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection is comprised of serial issues, pamphlets, leaflets, and circulated documents issued by Russian independent trade unions, relating to the labor movement in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2009.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
SMOT (Svobodnoe mezhprofessional'noe ob'edinenie trudiashchikhsia) records, Hoover Institution Archives
Rostislav Evdokimov papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Oleg Nikolaevich Moskvin papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
In the Soviet Union, labor unions were generally guided by Communist party policy, with the All-Union Central Council of Trade Unions (VTsSPS) in the forefront. Labor unions incorporated a majority of the labor force, as trade union membership was mandatory. The unions distributed and administered a wide range of social services to workers.
After the Perestroika in 1990, the Federation of Independent Trade Unions of Russia (FNPR) was established and became the post-Soviet successor of the VTsSPS, inheriting its resources as a monopolistic representative of workers' interests. At the same time, liberalization and economic reforms caused a tremendous wave of labor protest. Following the strike wave, the independence of the trade unions from the party was sealed in 1990 by the amendment of the Soviet constitution and the Soviet trade union law.
The mass protests that marked the end of the 1990s disappeared and since then social peace reigned, supported by economic growth and high world energy prices. The result was that most alternative unions either faded away or accommodated with management and shifted into a "traditional" company union. The Independent Miners' Union, which was the heart of the movement, disappeared. The trade unions of dockers and air traffic controllers, originally formed as independent professional unions from the traditional sector unions, struggled to survive. In some regions the regional administration used the trade unions as an instrument for monitoring local employers, just as the Communist Party did in the past, and the employer might approach the regional trade union organization with a request to establish a trade union branch in order to manage conflicts on the employers' behalf.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection documents the role of the trade unions in the political life, the structure of Soviet and post-Soviet trade unions. It contains serial issues, pamphlets, leaflets, and circulated documents issued by Russian independent trade unions.
Documents of "official" or "traditional" trade unions affiliated with the FNPR; and alternative or free labor unions independent from the FNPR are included. There are publications and reports of the Independent Trade Union of Miners (NPG), which marked the beginning of the alternative labor movement in Russia in 1991.
The collection also contains publications of the All-Russian Confederation of Labor (VKT), the Russian Confederation of Labor (KTR), and the Trade Union Association of Russia (SOTSPROF).
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically by publishing organization.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Labor movement--Soviet Union.; Labor movement--Russia (Federation)
Collection Contents
- Assotsiatsiia Sovetskoĭ professional'no-tekhnicheskoĭ shkoly, 1991 (Folder 1: 1)
- Cherezvychinyĭ s'ezd trudiashchikhsia Pridnestrov'ia, 1992 (Folder 1: 2)
- Demokraticheskoe dvizhenie "Nezavisimost',", 1989-2000 (Folder 1: 3-4)
- Federatsiia Nezavisimykh Profsoiuzov RSFSR, 1991-1999 (Folder 1: 5-13)
- Federatsiia Profsoiuzov Aviatsionnykh Dispetcherov, 1992-1997 (Folder 1: 14)
- Institut Svobodnykh Profsoiuzov, 1992-1997 (Folder 2: 1)
- International Labor Conferences, 1992-1993 (Folder 2: 2)
- Klub demokratizatsii profsoiuzov, circa 1992 (Folder 2: 3)
- Konfederatsiia svobodnykh profsoiuzov transporta Rossii, 1993-1998 (Folder 2: 4)
- Konfederatsiia Truda Rossii, 1991-1998 (Folder 2: 5-6)
- Leningradskaia (Sankt-Peterburgskaia) federatsiia profsoiuzov, 1991-1996 (Folder 2: 7-13)
- Mezhprofessional'nyĭ soiuz rabochikh Magnitki, circa 1990 (Folder 2: 14)
- Moskovskaia federatsiia profsoiuzov, 1991-1995 (Folder 2: 15)
- Nauchnyĭ tsentr profsoiuzov, 1993 (Folder 2: 16)
- Nezavisimyĭ professional'nyĭ soiuz "Svobodnyĭ Trud,", 1991 (Folder 2: 17)
- Nezavisimyĭ profsoiuz "Osvobozhdenie,", circa 1990 (Folder 2: 18)
- Nezavisimyĭ profsoiuz gorniakov Rossii, 1990-1998 (Folder 2: 19)
- Ob"edinenie profsoiuzov "Sotsprof,", 1989-1996 (Folder 3: 1-2)
- Ob"edinenie svobodnykh profsoiuzov "Spravedlivost',", 1993-1994 (Folder 3: 3)
- Ob"edinennyĭ vsesoiuznyĭ tsentral'nyĭ komitet svobodnykh profsoiuzov, 1994-1995 (Folder 3: 4)
- Ob"edinenie professional'nykh soiuzov trudiashchikhsia kooperativnykh predpriiatii SSSR, 1990 (Folder 3: 5)
- Obshcherossiiskoe obshchestvenno-politicheskoe dvizhenie "Soiuz Truda,", 1998 (Folder 3: 6)
- Permskiĭ Rabochiĭ Soiuz, 1987-1995 (Folder 3: 7-8)
- Pervyĭ s"ezd rabochilh dvizheniĭ I organizatsii trudiachshikhsia SSSR, 1990 (Folder 3: 9)
- Professional'nye Soiuzy RSFSR "Edinenie,", 1991-1992 (Folder 3: 10)
- Profkom "Energetik,", 1992 (Folder 3: 11)
- Profsoiuz "Studencheskaia Zashchita,", 1990 (Folder 3: 12)
- Profsoiuz mashinostroiteleĭ Rossiiskoĭ Federatsii, 1990 (Folder 3: 13)
- Profsoiuz voditileĭ taksi Sankt-Peterburga, 1990-1992 (Folder 3: 14)
- Proizvodstvennoe ob"edinenie "Kirovskiĭ Zavod,", 1991-1996 (Folder 3: 15)
- Rabochiĭ komitet Kuzbassa, 1989-1994 (Folder 3: 16)
- Rossiiskiĭ profsoiuz lokomotivnykh brigad, 1993-1999 (Folder 3: 17)
- Rossiskiĭ profsoiuz dokerov, 1995-1996 (Folder 3: 18)
- Russko-Amerikanskiĭ fond profsoiuznykh issledovaniĭ i obucheniia, 1993-1997 (Folder 3: 19)
- Russko-Amerikanskiĭ fond profsoiuznykh issledovaniĭ i obucheniia, (contd.), 1993-1997 (Folder 4: 1-9)
- Russko-Amerikanskiĭ fond profsoiuznykh issledovaniĭ i obucheniia, (contd.), 1993-1997 (Folder 5: 1-4)
- Soiuz rabotnikov profsoiuznykh sredstv massovoĭ informatsii "Profimform,", 1995 (Folder 5: 5)
- Svobodnoe Mezhprofessional'noe Ob"edinenie Trudiashchikhsia (SMOT), 1988-1997 (Folder 5: 6)
- Tovarishchestvo profsoiuzov Ekaterinburga, 1995-1996 (Folder 5: 7)
- Transnational Information Exchange (TIE), 1992-1999 (Folder 5: 8)
- Ural'skiĭ Profsoiuznyĭ Tsentr, 1995-1996 (Folder 5: 9)
- Zakony o profsoiuzakh, 1990-1999 (Folder 5: 10-15)